Hello everyone, my
name is Noah Chernick.
I'm one of your academic
medicine scholars
and today I'm here to
discuss valvular heart
disease, clinical
findings and diagnosis.
Before I start, I'd
like just to thank Dr.
Happel for all of
her support, help and
guidance in the creation
of this lecture.
If you have any additional
questions, comments
or concerns or you need
any additional resources
or you'd like to have
a discussion about this
lecture or any other
lecture I provided to you,
please feel free to email
me at the email below.
Here are our learning
objectives. I'm not
going to go through
each one, but I do
want to just discuss
one thing quickly.
I'm sure you guys have
heard this already from
my past lectures, but
it's important not just
to memorize things when
you can kind of try and
understand them from a
physiological aspect.
Murmurs are very high yield
with your in-house exams,
with boards, and more
importantly, when you're actually
in the hospital seeing
patients. A lot of patients
may have a heart murmur
or heart sound that isn't
necessarily normal. And instead
of you trying to memorize,
okay, the aortic stenosis
is heard here and it should
sound like this, try and
understand why the pathologic
presentation is occurring
due to physiology. That can
maybe help save a little
bit of brain space for
something that you actually
need to memorize. For example,
maybe a microbiome bug
that you really can't logic
your way through, you just
have to remember what it is.
So our lecture layout, we're
going to quickly review
normal heart sounds because
if we don't understand
what normal is, it's almost
impossible to realize what
the pathology is. We're
going to then go over
abnormal heart sounds and then
our systolic and diastolic
murmurs. And throughout all
of these examples, we're
going to be reviewing the
physical exam maneuvers
that either increase or
decrease the intensity of the
murmur. Those Those are
very, very important because
those help you narrow down
what the murmur can be
on exam questions and,
again, also in the hospital.
So, very briefly, I want
to review the cardiac
cycle. During systole,
the tricuspid and mitral
valves close, creating
that S1 heart sound.
And during diastole,
the aortic and pneumonic
valves close, creating
that S2 heart sound.
And again, just that normal
idea of why the valves
close is because there's
an equalization of
pressure between either
the right atrium and right
ventricle, which creates that
S1, or pressure equalization
between the right
ventricle and pulmonary
trunk, or you could also
talk about the left side.
So to continue on with our
physiologic heart sounds,
I want to briefly note this
little red heart up here.
So these are heart sounds.
I'm going to be playing
them throughout this lecture.
It's very important not
just to memorize the description
of the heart sound, but
actually have somewhat of
an idea of how it sounds.
So I'm going to play a normal
physiologic heart
for you right now.
So again, we have
our lub and our dub.
And essentially, the S1 lub,
again, due to the closure
of the mitral and tricuspid
valves, heard at the
beginning of systole. And
the mechanism is increased
ventricular pressure closes
the valves between the atria
and ventricles. So if you
can see right here, here's
our atrial pressure line,
this kind of dashed line.
Ventricular pressure
is this nice red
line. the AV valves
close. S1 occurs when
that pressure
essentially equalizes.
S2, due to the closure of
the aortic and pulmonic
valves. We also have
something called splitting of
S2. So during inspiration,
as we can see down
here on this graph, we
have an increased splitting
between the closure of the
aortic and pulmonic valves.
This is due to an
increased amount of preload
on the right side of the
heart during inspiration.
So it takes a longer time
for those pressures on
either side of the pulmonic
valve to equalize. So
P2 occurs after A2 as
there's more pressure between
the right ventricle and
the pulmonic arteries.
It's a similar idea. I
know we're looking at the
left side of the heart
here, but that S2 sound
occurs because the aortic
pressure, or in this case
it'd be the pulmonic
pressure and the right
ventricle, my apologies,
kind of equalize here. And
if you see down here,
during inspiration, we have
an increase of pressure on
the right side, decreased
of pressure on the left
side of the hearts.
And the S2, just to
continue on, it's louder
at the base. And
again, our mechanism is
decreased ventricular
pressure closes the valves.
So you can see here, as
we're dropping pressure,
it kind of equalizes
with our aortic and
pulmonic valves or
arteries, and it essentially
will close because of
the pressure change.
We have five main areas
of auscultation for the
heart. You have your
aortic, which is the right
second intercostal space,
pulmonic, which is your
left second intercostal
space, tricuspid, left lower
sternal border at the
fourth intercostal space,
mitral is the left fifth
intercostal space, and
Herb's point is the left
third intercostal space.
It's important to have
a general idea of where
these five areas are,
not just remembering, oh,
aortic, pulmonic,
tricuspid. Actually, no,
aortic is right second
intercostal, pulmonic is
left. A lot of test
questions will not tell you
there's an auscultation
over the aortic region.
They'll say the right
second intercostal space.
Additionally, this little
graph down here can be very
helpful for you if you're
having difficulties remembering
where a murmur is best
heard. It kind of breaks it
down into where the systolic
and diastolic murmurs will
be will be best heard
depending on these five areas.
So splitting of S2 to continue
on with that conversation.
A2 typically occurs before
P2 and occurs during
inspiration. So like we
said, the aortic valve
will close before the
pulmonic valve during
inspiration. We best hear
this in the pulmonic area.
So during inspiration,
A2 occurs before P2. The
mechanism, we spoke about
this, but just to review,
inspiration decreases
intrathoracic pressure, essentially
allowing for higher volumes
or higher preload on
that right ventricle and
right side of the heart.
We have more volume in the
right ventricle. We have a
larger pressure difference
between the right ventricle
and pulmonic artery. So
during systole, that pulmonic
valve will stay open
longer because the pressure
gradient is wider. And
remember, the valves only close
when the pressure on either
side of the valve is equal.
We also can have pathologic
splitting of S2. You
can have atrial septal
defects causing a fixed
splitting, which we see
over here, which means that
there's no change between
inspiration and expiration.
Aortic stenosis and
left bundle branch block
create a paradoxical
splitting of S2. So that
means we only see splitting
during expiration.
And then finally, pulmonary
arterial hypertension
and stenosis, you see
wide splitting, which
means that splitting
is present both during
expiration and inspiration,
but we still have
a larger gap between A2
and P2 in inspiration.
So continuing on with
our conversation of split
S2, the pathologic
regions, so our fixed
splitting does not
disappear during expiration.
With atrial septal defect,
this is essentially because
the right side of the
heart is going to have a
higher amount of preload
because of that hole between
the left and right atrium.
So blood is going to
rush from the left to the
right, increasing right side
of preload, and it's
essentially the same mechanism
as inspiration at that
point. We have excess blood
in the right ventricle
regardless of inspiration.
Paradoxical
splitting of S2, that
occurs usually
during expiration,
and that's because during
expiration, the left side of
the heart has higher levels
of preload, and we're
going to have aortic stenosis.
So essentially, it's going
to take longer for that
valve to equalize and close
because the valve is stiff.
It takes longer to close.
Wide splitting, normal S2
is exaggerated, so that's
pulmonary arterial
hypertension and stenosis.
For PAH, you have increased
pulmonary arterial
pressure that increases
the duration of
systole in the right
ventricle because that
right ventricle must
overcome increased
pressure gradients to
open that pulmonic valve.
In stenosis,
again, the valve is
stiff. It just takes
longer to close.
Don't worry too much about
the pathology here. This
is not a pathology lecture,
I'm only giving you
this information because
if it's easier for you to
kind of rationalize why
this is occurring due to
pathophysiology, then you
have one less thing you
have to memorize. However,
if you just want to remember
that a wide split is due
to pulmonary arterial
hypertension or stenosis,
you should be just fine.
Continuing on with our
conversation of abnormal heart
sounds, you have two additional
ones. You have S3 and
S4. S3 can be normal in
well-conditioned athletes,
children, and pregnant women.
Abnormal, it's usually due
to aortic valve regurg or
dilated cardiomyopathy. And
the S3 heart sound in general
is due to blood rushing
into an already filled or
volume overloaded chamber. And
here's what S3 sounds like.
It occurs just after S2.
S4 is typically a compliance
issue. It occurs right
before S1 and it's due to
blood kind of hitting stiff
ventricular walls. Think
about a more muscular
heart or heart that doesn't
necessarily want to relax.
Here's what the
S4 sound is like.
Types of murmurs, you could
break them down into a
stenosis, which is a problem
with opening the valve.
Also can be called a
forward-flowing murmur. And
your pathophys connection
here is when a valve does
not open properly or
fully, the heart chamber
upstream or the heart chamber
behind that valve has to
increase the amount of
force to open or get blood
through that valve that's
denounced. This usually
causes hypertrophy and
thickening of that chamber.
Regurgitation is the
opposite, so that's a problem
with closing the valve.
It's also known as a
backwards flowing murmur.
Your pathophist connection
here is when a valve
cannot close properly,
the heart chamber upstream
or the one before the
valve will experience
increased blood and volumes.
This usually causes
dilation of that chamber.
So there are a few different
ways we can describe a
murmur. You can describe
it via the sound. Crescendo
decrescendo, that means it
rises and falls in intensity.
Plateau, it's about the
same intensity throughout.
Crescendo just grows
louder, then it disappears.
Decrescendo, it
only grows softer.
For location, if it's
louder at the base, it's
typically something
like an aortic issue. If
it's louder at the apex,
it's a mitral issue.
Radiation. You could have
sounds that radiate into the
carotid, such as in aortic
stenosis, or the axilla in
mitral regurgitation. Your
quality. It could be described
as blowing, harsh, or
rumbling. And then your pitch.
It could be low, medium,
and high. You'll see each
of the murmurs we go over
in detail will actually be
described with multiple of
these kinds of combinations.
So I'm sure this was
already gone over during
DPR, but you can grade
murmurs on a scale of
one to six. I'm not
going to go over the
descriptions of each one
because I know you all
can read, but essentially
one is the very faint,
the least heard, and
six is very very loud.
You may not even
need to place your
stethoscope on the
chest to hear it.
So dynamic auscultation.
There are many different ways
that we can increase or
decrease the intensity of a
murmur depending on what
type of murmur it is. So our
first kind of way to understand
where the murmur maybe
is, is respiration. So during
inhalation, it increases
the intensity of any right
-sided murmur. Again, if you
remember, inspiration will
increase our right ventricular
preload and decrease our
left ventricular preload.
Expiration usually
increases the intensity
of any left-sided
murmurs. Again, that is
going to increase left
ventricular preload.
Valsalva maneuver, so
essentially that's bearing down
by trying to exhale
with a lot of
force, but their
mouth is closed.
Valsalva maneuver will
decrease your right
ventricular preload,
left ventricular
preload, and left
ventricular afterload.
So all across the board,
decreasing. Your key use
here, it can distinguish
between aortic stenosis versus
as hypertrophic obstructive
cardiomyopathy because
the Valsalva maneuver will
decrease the intensity of
aortic stenosis but increase
the intensity of hokum.
Squatting from a standing
position or leg raising, this
increases the amount of
preload because the blood
stored in the legs will
return to the heart. So right
and left ventricular preload
increases. No change in left
ventricular afterload. Your
key is here. It softens
the murmur of hokum and moves
the click in mitral valve
prolapse later in systole.
Don't really worry about
hokum here. That's not a
valvular pathology, but we
will go into great detail
about mitral valve prolapse.
Standing from a seated
or squatted position.
Blood will pool in the legs.
That results in decreased
preload. So it's kind of
the opposite of the
squatting from standing. This
one is standing from a
seated position. So it's
similar to the valsalva,
the keys here, you move the
click and mitral valve
prolapse earlier in systole.
And finally, hand grip,
so gripping onto something
with a lot of force,
increases afterload.
That usually increases
the intensity of any left
-sided regurgent, also known
as a back-flowing murmur.
So we can split our murmurs
into systolic and diastolic
murmurs. We're going to
start with our systolic.
Our first systolic
murmur is going to
be aortic stenosis.
Here's the sound.
As you can hear, it's
this kind of crescendo
-decrescendo systolic murmur.
Here's a little graph here.
The causes of aortic
stenosis, post-inflammatory
scarring from rheumatic
heart disease,
a senile calcified aortic
stenosis, that's essentially
you see someone who's
maybe a little bit older
in age, they just have a
normal calcified valve.
You also could have
a calcification of a
congenitally deformed valve.
This is someone with a
bicuspid valve, occurs at
a younger age. Your murmur
description, as you just
heard, it's a crescendo
decrescendo systolic murmur,
best heard in the aortic
area. Makes sense. Aortic
stenosis is heard in
the aortic area, right
second intercostal space.
A key describer
here is also aortic
stenosis radiates
to the carotids.
With dynamic auscultation,
this is a forward flow
murmur. So anything that
drops our preload is going to
decrease intensity. Anything
that limits the amount
of blood moving through the
aortic valve is going to
decrease intensity. So with
that in mind, standing or
valsalva maneuvers that
decrease preload will decrease
the intensity of aortic
stenosis. Hand grip increases
our afterload will also
decrease the intensity.
Both squatting and
leg raises, which both
increase the amount
of preload, will
increase the intensity
of aortic stenosis.
Your clinical presentation.
It can cause paradoxical
splitting of S2 as the aortic
valve takes longer to open
and also eventually close
as the disease progresses.
So an acronym for kind
of the presentation is
SAD, syncope, angina, and
dyspnea on exertion. You
also can have respiratory
crackles, and this is
due to left ventricular
hypertrophy and also
left-sided heart failure,
allowing for blood to
kind of pull up on the
left side of the heart and
eventually move into the
pulmonary circulation.
You also have something
called pulsus parvis
etartus, weak and delayed
pulse in the carotids.
You can also have an
S4 heart sound as blood
rushes into the stiff
hypertrophied ventricular
walls as you can see
in the image down here.
You have a larger
and more lateral
point of maximal
impulse as well, so
that point moves
further to the left.
Your pathologic changes
to the heart here,
left ventricular hypertrophy
occurs as an adaptive
measure to counteract
the increased force
required to eject blood
from the left ventricle.
So now moving over to pulmonic
stenosis, here's
what it sounds like.
It sounds fairly similar
to aortic stenosis. So
let's go over causes,
description, and then some
dynamic auscultation to
help you figure out the
differences between aortic
and pulmonic stenosis.
So our causes, congenital,
torology of fallow,
carcinoid syndrome
affects both the tricuspid
and pulmonary valves, you
also have endocarditis.
Your murmur description.
Crescendo, decrescendo,
mid-systolic, high-pitched
murmur heard at the pulmonic
area of auscultation.
That's our left second
intercostal space. Different than
aortic stenosis where we
would hear it at the right
second intercostal space.
It also radiates to the
left shoulder and the neck,
also known as the axilla.
Dynamic auscultation. It's
a forward flow murmur.
So increased intensity
with increased
preload, decreased
intensity with
decreased preload, or
increased afterload.
And additionally,
increased intensity with
inspiration. This is the
biggest difference, this
last one, increased
intensity with inspiration.
Aortic stenosis,
you should have a
decreased intensity
with inspiration.
Pulmonic, you have
that increase.
Clinical presentation
can cause wide splitting
of S2 as the right
ventricle takes longer to
eject blood through
the calcified pulmonic
valve. You could also
have vaginal chest pain.
Moving on to mitral regurg,
here's what it sounds like. To
our causes,
mitral valve prolapse
can precede mitral
regurgitation. We'll talk
about this in a few slides.
Post-myocardial infarction,
acute papillary muscle
rupture, because remember,
these papillary muscles
help tie down that mitral
valve to the separation
between the left atrium
and left ventricle. Chronic
infective endocarditis,
vegetation and valve deformities
on the leaflets of the
valve can also contribute
to mitral regurge, rheumatic
heart disease, inflammation,
and damage to the mitral
valve. You could also
have congenital deformities,
so anything that weakens
the collagen of the valve.
That's Marfan syndrome,
Ehlers-Danlos syndrome,
osteogenesis imperfecta.
You could also have
ventricular disease causing it.
A dilated cardiomyopathy
increases the opening of
the mitral valve. So
it's now too wide for the
leaflets to fully close that
separation between the atria
and ventricle and allows
blood to pass through.
Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy,
that anterior
leaflet is pulled
towards the thickening
wall, also allowing
blood to pass through.
Your murmur description.
It's a blowing holosystolic
murmur. Best heard at
the apex of the heart.
Left and fifth intercostal
space at the midclavicular
line. It usually obscures
S1. reminder S1 is due
to mitral valve closure
so if we have issues with
that mitral valve closing
the valve will not close
properly and we usually
don't hear S1 so for mitral
regurgitation dynamic
auscultation the intensity
decreases with inspiration
this is a left-sided
valvular pathology we see
increases in intensity with
increased preload and
afterload so with increased
preload we have more blood
in that left ventricle
and it allows a higher
opportunity or more of an
opportunity to escape back
through the mitral valve.
Increase in afterload, we
have an increased resistance
for blood leaving the
aortic valve. This
increases the pressure in
the left ventricle causing
more blood to pass back
through the mitral valve.
We see a decrease in intensity
with a decreased preload.
For your clinical
presentation, pulmonary
crackles, elevated jugular
venous distension, and
lower extremity edema.
All of these changes
that you see here are
usually due to issues
with left heart failure.
So because that left
atrium will dilate and
it's moving backwards,
eventually you have
congestion in the
pulmonic vasculature
and then moving on to
right-sided heart
failure. So these clinical
presentations are
usually due to that.
For pathologic changes
to the heart, the preload
in the left atrium will
increase as the blood moves
backwards from the left
ventricle. During diastole,
when the atria contracts,
this extra blood
will move back into the
left ventricle, increasing
the end diastolic pressure
in the left ventricle.
This backup continues
from the left atria as the
pulmonary veins become
congested. We have increased
pulmonary capillary pressure
and pulmonary edema.
You also can't see pillow
orthopnea. Anyone with left
-sided heart failure can
present with pillow orthopnea,
which essentially means
if a patient presents
and says they wake up with
dyspnea at night or they
feel like they can't sleep
at night without three,
four, or five pillows
under their head, you could
think about some form of
left-sided heart failure.
So mitral valve prolapse
is similar to mitral
regurgitation, typically
occurs before it
in some cases. Here's
what it sounds like.
So the key here is there's some
form of click that is heard.
The other thing to keep in mind
is the dynamic auscultation
is going to be very
different. So let's go over
pathophysiology first. The
leaflets are attached to the
ventricle via the chordae
tendinae which with the help
of the papillary muscles.
In mitral valve prolapse,
the leaflets and chordae
tendinae are weakened allowing
for the leaflets to
balloon out into the left
atrium during systole. So
again kind of balloons out.
This also shows some
form of regurge which
can occur together
but as you can see
through this kind of
little white aspect here
it's ballooning up
into the left atrium.
Your causes, degeneration
can occur so irregular
middle layer of the valve
leaflet. This leaflet
thickens and the chordae
tendine weaken. Increased
deposition of mucopolysaccharides
in the spongiosa
layer, which is the
middle layer of the valve.
You could also have
connective tissue diseases,
Marfan syndrome, EDS,
osteogenesis, and perfecta.
Marfan is an auto-dominant
defect, fibrillin production,
which cross-links elastin.
Essentially, that's
kind of a clinical reminder.
You typically can see some
correlations between some
congenital diseases and
these heart murmurs. So just
something to keep in mind.
Mitral valve disease.
Infective endocarditis. These
scar the leaflets and weaken
the chordae tendineae.
Post myocardial infarction.
You could have tearing
of the papillary muscles
and rheumatic fever. This
is inflammation allowing
the leaflets to stretch.
The murmur description.
It's a mid to systolic click
and then it's a little
bit of a crescendo after
that. The click is the
mitral chordae tendine
snapping as the leaflet
prolapses into the left atrium.
So as you can see here's
your click and then it
increases intensity into
S2. For dynamic auscultation
the click changes with
the amount of left
ventricular preload. If we
decrease preload it's an
earlier click meaning that
click goes closer to S1.
If we increase preload,
it's a later click,
meaning that click
goes closer to S2.
So this is not necessarily
a textbook explanation,
but it's something that
helped me out. Think about
the click occurring at
some predetermined volume
that is less than the left
ventricular and diastolic
pressure. So if we have
more preload or a higher
afterload, that click is
going to occur later in
systole because we need
more blood to leave that
left ventricle in order
to hit that predetermined
click volume. The opposite
occurs when we have a
decreased amount of preload,
so that left diastolic
and pressure is going to
be a little bit closer to
that click volume, so it's
going to occur earlier.
For clinical
presentation, think about
very similar to
mitral regurgitation.
Pathologic changes
to the heart, it
can eventually lead
to mitral regurg.
So the next murmur is tricuspid
regurgitation. Here's
what it sounds like.
That description, it's
going to be holosystolic,
so fully throughout
the systole, high
-pitched, and kind of
that blowing sound.
Pathophysiology, it's
due to right ventricle
dilation, which does
not allow the tricuspid
valve to fully close
during systole. Your
causes, again, due to
right ventricle dilation.
This could be due to
pulmonary hypertension.
Epstein's anomaly, so
that's a congenital
defect, downward
displacement of the tricuspid
valve into the right
ventricle, can be due to
lithium in utero, and finally,
infective endocarditis.
That is usually seen
in IV drug users.
Remember, the tricuspid
valve is the first
valve Staph aureus will
encounter in the heart.
For the description,
it's a holosystolic,
high-pitched, blowing sound.
Loudest in the tricuspid
area, you have a barely
audible S1 with a
split S2. For dynamic
auscultation, the main
thing here is increases
of inspiration. This is
a right-sided heart sound
or heart murmur, so
you would expect that.
For your clinical
presentation, it's
usually asymptomatic.
Severe cases may present
with symptoms of
right heart failure,
so that's kind of
peripheral edema, maybe
hepatic congestion,
things like that.
It can create changes in
jugular venous waveform,
so you have these giant
CV waves during systole.
So here's your normal,
you kind of have this nice
drop, but because you have
this regurgitation during
systole, there's actually
not that drop as fluid or
blood is going to be
pushed back into the right
atrium, so you're going to
have that spike in the CV.
So we are now going to move
on to our diastolic murmurs.
So the first diastolic
murmur is going to be aortic
regurgitation. The
pathophysiology essentially
boiled down is that once
blood exits the heart during
systole, it passes back
through the aortic valve into
the left ventricle. So
that's usually called the
regurgent fraction. So the
amount of blood that moves
back afterwards. You see
a higher or increased
left ventricle and diastolic
pressure. You also see
a larger amount or a higher
pressure during systole
because the left ventricle
also has to eject more.
Some causes, bicuspid
aortic valve, endocarditis,
aortic root dilation,
rheumatic fever,
and hypertension. The
murmur sounds like this,
so you can hear that diastolic,
decrescendo, high
-pitched, blowing murmur.
And depending on the cause,
you can hear it in two
different areas. So aortic
root dilation, it's at
the base, so right upper
sternal border, and
valvular pathology, you
usually hear it around the left
sternal border. For dynamic
excitation, it's going
to be louder during
expiration. Remember, this
is a left-sided heart
murmur, so usually expiration
will increase the intensity
of any of those, and
if the patient is sitting
up and leaning forward.
So for clinical presentation,
you're going to see a
hyperdynamic pulse, which
is essentially a large
difference between the systolic
and diastolic blood pressure
readings. You also may
see head bobbing or very
violent or forceful pulse that
you feel in the periphery,
you could see signs of
left heart failure so
pillow orthopnea or paroxysmal
nocturnal dyspnea. You
also could hear an S3
heart sound due to dilated
cardiomyopathy. For the
pathologic changes to the heart,
it can progress to left
-sided heart failure. Again,
this is a left-sided heart
murmur. The valve is affecting
the left side so we can
see some changes occurring
resulting in left-sided
heart failure. Essentially,
what happens is to manage
to increase end diastolic
pressures and the force
required to achieve systole,
the left ventricle will
hypertrophy, causing eccentric
hypertrophy. And then
essentially as that end diastolic
volume continues to
increase, that left ventricle
eventually dilates. So the
end cause is actually going
to be a dilated cardiomyopathy,
which causes that
S3 heart sound. So I know
it says here you see some
hypertrophy and then it
leads to cardiomyopathy, but
essentially think that the
end diastolic volume is just
building and building and
building and building, and
eventually the only way the
heart is going to be able
to manage that is through
a dilated cardiomyopathy.
It can cause heart failure.
The congestion, again,
will move backwards
through the system, seeing
those signs like pulmonary
complications, edema,
dyspnea, pillow orthopnea,
things I just spoke about.
So for pulmonary regurgitation,
it's fairly uncommon.
You hypertension, or
infective endocarditis. For
the murmur description, it's
going to be high-pitched,
early decrescendo murmur.
It can usually be heard
at ERB's point, so left
third or fourth intercostal
space. In the description,
you have a normal
S1 with a split S2, so P2
is going to be occurring
after A2. That should kind
of make sense. Again, if
we remember back when we
were talking about split
S2s, if we have more volume
in that right ventricle,
it's going to take longer
for that P2 to occur.
Dynamic auscultation,
again really the only
difference here versus
aortic regurgitation is now
we're going to see an
increase in intensity during
inspiration, whereas
aortic regurgitation is
going to be increase of
intensity in expiration.
For clinical presentation
really the only
thing that you can
notice is a palpable P2.
So mitral stenosis,
your pathophysiology
is usually due to a
narrowing or hardening
of the mitral valve.
You usually see an
increase in left atrial
volume as a result.
For the causes, most common
cause is rheumatic heart
disease. So you see this
a lot on test questions.
You actually see this a lot
on rotations. I had a few
emergency room visits
where I actually heard the
mitral stenosis kind of murmur
and you know learning they
had some kind of childhood
strep throat that never
got treated and it
progressed. So think about
complications of acute rheumatic
fever due to group A strep,
strep pyogenes, typically
a longer-term process.
So inflammation slowly
calcifies the valve.
You also may hear
this as the fish mouth
presentation of the mitral
valve. Also can be due
to calcification. Think
about age-related. You
also could have some
results or side effects
from radiation. So
Hodgkin's lymphoma, chest
malignancies that receive
extensive radiation.
The murmur description,
it sounds like this.
So you hear that opening
snap followed by a low
-pitched diastolic rumble.
The opening snap is due to
an abrupt stop of the
leaflet tips due to fusion.
So again, remember, it's
stenotic, it's calcified,
it doesn't move very well.
So that snap sound is just
the leaflet's really
not moving as well as it
should. You best hear it at
the apex of the heart. And
again, as the disease
severity increases, the
opening snap occurs earlier
in diastole. So this is
due to an increase in left
atrial pressure, forcing
the mitral valve to snap
open earlier in diastole.
So again, this kind of
explanation may not be the
most scientific, but I
want to give you some just
tips and general ideas of
how to simplify these things.
So think about over
time, you're going to see
increased left atrial volumes.
That's going to create
more force, more fluid
moving through the mitral
valve during diastole, so
that snap occurs earlier.
For dynamic auscultation,
we'll increase in intensity
with expiration and when
positioned in the left
lateral decubitus position.
Decreases in intensity
with decreased preload. For
clinical presentation, exertional
dyspnea, pillow orthopnea,
paraximal, nocturnal
dyspnea. Again, you kind of
see your left heart failure
kind of symptoms. Your
pathologic changes to the
heart. Increases in left
atrial volume will cause
pulmonary edema and congestion.
It also can cause atrial
fibrillation due to the
dilation of the left atrium.
You could also have a
thromboembolism. Left atrial
dilation can allow for slow
moving blood to pool in the
left atrium. So if you see
a test question where maybe
someone has a stroke, there's
no signs of an atrial or
ventricular septal defect.
Maybe you start thinking
about atrial fibrillation
or mitral stenosis causing
that dilated left atrium.
Tricuspid stenosis, it's
fairly similar again to
mitral, the pathophysiology.
It's usually
inflammation or chronic
injury causing fibrosis and
calcium deposition. So
this kind of leads to a
thickened and stiffened
valve. The valve does not
open fully during diastole,
increases pressures
in the right atrium
and the vena cava. Your
causes, again, it could be
rheumatic heart disease,
atrial myxoma, tumor
that can block the valve,
non-bacterial thrombotic
endocarditis. You see
that typically with lupus.
For the murmur description,
it's a fairly similar
opening snap followed
by a soft mid-diastolic
rumble. It's best heard
here at the fourth
intercostal space at the left
parasternal border. For
dynamic auscultation,
it's an increase in preload.
You see an increased
intensity. So anything
with inspiration, leg
raising, or squats, whenever
you decrease preload,
standing valsalva usually
decreases intensity.
Again, if you've gotten to
this point, you may have
noticed some fairly common
things. Usually with stenosis,
anything that's forward
flowing, anything that
increases the preload, usually
increases the intensity.
And anything that's
a regurgitation,
anything that kind of
increases afterload,
may increase the
intensity in that aspect.
So for the clinical
presentation fairly asymptomatic
until it's severe. You
could have palpitations,
fatigue, cold skin.
This is usually due to
lower cardiac output.
You could have left heart
failure as a result of
an inadequate preload.
A big key you may see
every now and then giant A
waves on the JV waveform
as the right atrium is
contracting against a
narrow tricuspid valve. So
essentially that right atrium
is trying to contract and
it's getting resistance
kind of you can see here
that massive a wave of
increase of pressure because
the tricuspid valve just
isn't allowing any forward
moving blood into that right
ventricle you could also
have kusumel sign and that's
a paradoxical increase in
jugular venous pressure
during inspiration it's not
specific to tricuspid stenosis
it can occur at any point
where blood flow from the
vena cava to the pulmonary
vasculature is compromised so
that's essentially any form
of tricuspid valve disease.
It could be, in theory,
even like a pulmonic valve
disease. Also think of
constrictive pericarditis or
restrictive cardiomyopathy. So
just for completion sake, I
want to quickly just review
and go over these non
-valvular murmurs. This is
somewhat outside the scope
of this lecture per se, but
these are things you will
hear. So ventricular septal
defect, it's a systolic murmur.
That makes sense, right?
The ventricles contract
during systole, so if
there's a hole, the blood
would be flowing through
during systole. So it
sounds like a holosystolic,
harsh-sounding murmur.
Some of it sounds like
this, and it's best heard
at the tricuspid area.
Atrial septal defect, it's
usually a wide fixed splitting
of the S2 due to an
increased volume in the right
atrium. You may see right
heart dilation due to fluid
overload. we discussed this
one a little bit here's what
it sounds like so with
that you kind of hear that
that murmur sound and then
the split s2 finally patent
ductus arteriosus it's more
of a continuous machine like
murmur it's best heard at
the left intraclavicular
area louder in s2 it almost
sounds like very much like a
machine it's fairly unique
here's what it sounds like
it's fairly
continuous. There's no
real distinction
of S1 or S2 there.
So I know that was a
lot. Murmurs can be very
complicated. There's a lot
to remember between dynamic
auscultations, presentations,
causes, pathophysiologic
changes. So I want to
go over some general
rules and considerations
that you can use both
during your exams and board
study and also when you're
in the clinic in the
hospital actually listening
to patients who potentially
have these murmurs.
So the first thing
I want to quickly
review is dynamic auscultation.
So whenever we think about
a drop preload, decreased
amount of preload, so
standing and valsalvin
maneuvers, we're going
to drop the amount of
fluid in the heart that
usually decreases most murmurs
involving any form of
fluid moving across a
valve. So that's both
regurgitation and stenosis.
The one exception is
mitral valve prolapse.
Remember in mitral valve
prolapse, there's a click
that occurs at some set
point that's less than
the normal amount of blood
present at the end of
diastole, so if we drop
the amount of preload,
it's going to actually
make this click
occur sooner,
because the time it
takes to get to that
set point is less.
So again,
standing in Valsalva
drops preload,
decreases intensity
of most murmurs.
Passive leg raise
increases the amount of
preload, so an increased
amount of fluid in the
heart usually increases
the intensity of most
murmurs involving fluid
moving across the valve,
so exact opposite of
the standing valsalva.
So we would see an increase
in intensity in most of
these murmurs. Again, the
one difference, mitral valve
prolapse likes to be difficult
and annoying. It takes
longer for that click to occur
because we have more blood
at the end of diastole, so
it takes a longer time to
achieve that click set
point where the fluid is the
amount, correct amount to
cause that collect to happen.
For squatting, you see an
increase in preload
and afterload.
It's a little bit variable
with what happens, but in
general, think about an
increased amount of fluid in
the heart. So similar to
above, we're going to increase
amount of preload. The
afterload also increases,
but the preload is still
greater. So think about squatting
about usually in the terms
of increased preload.
Hand grip is usually where
they want to go to if
they're going to talk about
increases in afterload.
Usually hand grip
only affects the left
side of murmurs because
afterload isn't really
affected in the
pulmonary vasculature.
Afterload will increase
the effects of any
backward flowing murmur.
So think about aortic
and mitral regurg,
ventral, septal defects.
It's going to decrease
the intensity of aortic
stenosis. that is a
forward-flowing murmur.
The final one,
inspiration increases
anything on the right side.
If you are reading a
question stem and you
are caught up between
tricuspid and mitral
regurgitation,
look for what's going
on with inspiration.
If it gets louder, more
intense during inspiration,
it is a right side
of murmur. Helps you
eliminate, in theory,
could be almost half
the murmurs that you've
learned here today.
So here is a chart. If you
look down each of the dynamic
auscultation maneuvers,
it's really mitral valve
prolapse that likes to be
the difficult child. So
decreased preload, decreased
intensities of everything in
the systolic category besides
mitral valve prolapse,
increases of
preload, it's going
to be essentially the opposite.
The squat, if you remember,
it's fairly similar
to essentially just an
increase in preload.
And for hand grip, if we
increase the amount of
afterload, it's going to
decrease the amount in
the aortic stenosis, going
to increase the intensity
in mitral recurge.
And again, inspiration,
just see right
-sided. So tricuspid
and pulmonic stenosis.
So for our diastolic
murmurs, again, fairly
similar. You drop the preload,
decrease in intensity.
We increase our preload,
so both leg raise
and a squat you're going
to increase intensity.
Hand grip, when we increase
after load, it only
usually affects left-sided
heart murmurs. Anything
that's backward flowing,
so your aortic and mitral
regurgitation, is going to
be increase in intensity.
Anything that's
forward flowing, so
your mitral stenosis
and aortic stenosis,
are going to decrease
in intensity.
And finally, inspiration
only affects right
-sided in terms of increases
in intensity, so you're
going to see an increase
in intensity with
pulmonic regurgitation
and tricuspid stenosis.
So for your complications
with stenosis,
think about increases in
pressure in the chamber
before the disease
valve. So we're gonna
have hypertrophy and
a backflow of blood.
For regurg, think about
an increased volume in the
chamber before the disease
valve. So fairly similar.
Again, it's also backflow,
but this time dilation, right?
There's increased fluid
rushing back into it. The
heart isn't necessarily
becoming hypertrophied because
it doesn't have to force,
use more force to push the
blood forward. This also
leads to heart failure if
untreated. When we talk
about heart failure, our left
-sided murmurs and heart failure,
usually you see pulmonary
congestion and edema,
cough, dyspnea, orthopnea,
paroxysmal nocturnal
dyspnea. So you see any
stem, any patient that
comes into the clinic says,
oh, I have to sleep
in a recliner. Oh, I
need three or four
pillows to sleep at night.
Immediate alarm bells
should be going off. This
patient may be suffering from
left-sided heart failure.
Right-sided heart
failure, it's usually
engorgement of the systemic
and portal venous system.
So that's hepatomegaly,
jugular venous
distension, peripheral
edema. And remember, you
can have symptoms of
right-sided heart failure
due to left-sided heart
failure. Essentially,
the heart failure is
becoming so severe it's
passed all the way to the
right side of the heart.
So finally, before we jump
into some questions, I
have a few algorithm slides.
So first in the clinic,
first thing you should
be doing when you're
auscultating is taking your
time, listening clearly,
listening to all the different
points of auscultation.
You have to ask
yourself, is this normal?
If you don't know what the
murmur is, but you hear
a murmur, that's usually
okay if you're a third year.
Most attendings and most
residents will appreciate
you just took the time
to listen and at least be
confident enough to know
that something is not right.
So, if you realize that
it's abnormal, then you need
to ask yourself, what is
this sound? Is it an S3, S4
heart sound, or is this
an actual valvular murmur?
If you think it's a
valvular murmur, then we
need to go into, when
is this occurring? Is
it during systole,
diastole, continuous? If
we can narrow it down
to when it's occurring,
it essentially halves the
amount of options, right?
We had five systolic murmurs,
four diastolic murmurs.
So if you can identify
that, okay, this murmur is
occurring during systole,
you knock out almost half.
So the next question you
want to ask is, where am I
hearing this murmur?
Think about your areas of
auscultation, and more
specifically, is the murmur
radiating anywhere? Those
can be dead giveaways, right?
Murm radiates to
the carotids, think
about aortic stenosis,
for an example.
Finally, you can move
into more niche areas, so
what does the murmur sound
like? Blowing, crescendo,
decrescendo, etc. Does
it also change with any
dynamic oscillation, which
is actually step six.
So, very simply, we have
talked about this, left versus
right. Does inspiration
make it better or worse?
You also think about maneuvers
increasing or decreasing
preload we could have hand
grip maneuvers as well
finally think about clinical
signs is this patient
presenting with any signs of
left or right heart failure
signs of any other clinical
manifestations this
could also include the history
if your patient comes in
with a history of untreated
group a strep infections
okay think about maybe there's
an issue with rheumatic
fever and mitral stenosis
or something like that.
For exam questions,
I have bad news.
Board questions
usually now includes
audio sounds for the
murmur questions.
I have this both
on Comlex and STEP,
so know they're out
there. I'm not sure if
they're experimental
or if they're now being
graded, but you do need
to feel comfortable
listening to murmurs
during your board exams.
Typically you'll see
case presentation that
helps you move into
the right direction, so
essentially that heart sound
is just a confirmatory,
just like, yes, this
is aortic stenosis or
something like that. So
go through your algorithm.
Where is this occurring? Is it
systolic or diastolic murmur?
Are they giving me the
location of auscultation?
Are they telling me
about any signs of
heart failure, left,
right, or both. Then
we think about our
dynamic auscultation.
Usually they're nice,
usually you may see
something like an
increase or decrease of
preload maneuvers,
something like that.
Definitely go through
patient history. So think
about, I just spoke about
this, history of untreated
strep throat, mitral valve
issues, right? Outerly
individual with dyspnea,
radiations, carotids,
aortic stenosis, usually
can just occur due to
age. Pillar orthopnea,
left-sided heart failure.
Before you actually
click play and listen to
the murmur, have an idea
of what you think the
murmur should sound
like, right? If you think
this is aortic stenosis,
you should be thinking,
okay, crescendo decrescendo
systolic murmur.
If you listen to it and
it sounds like that,
perfect, we've moved on.
You're not relying on
just your ears for the
question. You're more
confirming it after
going through the sound.
So here are a few summary
slides. I have a link to
all the heart sounds I
use. This is a fairly good
link if you want to just
listen to them. Here's a
little bit more of a picture
looking at the different
types. They're all labeled,
so this is more aortic
stenosis, regurg, pneumonic
stenosis, regurg, and
whatnot. So if you're
more of a visual learner
than liking to just kind of
listen to things, this is
also fairly helpful. I
love using these to study.
Here's some dynamic
auscultation, quick tips, and
then we actually go into
each murmur over these
next two slides looking at
a graph. So you can kind
of look at this when you're
reviewing before your
comps or board exams and
maybe go back to this.
So let's go over
some questions.
I'm not going to read
the prompt because I'm
sure you are all tired
of hearing my voice.
So essentially, which
of the following is
most likely to be
seen in this patient?
So the first thing I want to
think about is
my question stem.
Dizziness, shortness
of breath, 75.
Okay, what am I
already thinking about?
Right, he's older,
could be an aortic
calcification,
something like that.
Chest discomfort,
relieved with rest.
History of hypertension. All
right, maybe a hypertrophic,
you know, enlarged heart,
something like that.
Physical exam. So
here's the the bread and
butter. Loud mid to
late systolic murmur,
right upper sternal border
radiating to the carotids.
It's throwing the answer
at you guys, which is the
following most likely to also
be seen in this patient. All
right, so you think easy.
Aortic stenosis. It's heard
in the aortic area. It's
a loud mentholate systolic
murmur. Radiates the
carotids. He's old. This fits
perfectly. Now you actually
need to take one step further
and remember what the different
dynamic auscultations.
So decrease in murmur intensity
with a valsalva maneuver.
That's true, right?
We're going to drop
our preload, so we
drop our intensity.
I'm sorry for this terrible
writing. I won't do it again.
Decrease in murmur
intensity with squatting,
right? Squatting usually
increases preload.
So we'll actually see an
increase in intensity.
Increase in murmur intensity
with hand grip, that's
wrong. We would see a
drop in intensity with
a hand grip because we
are increasing afterload.
Increase in murmur
intensity with inspiration,
wrong. This is only
for right sighted heart
murmurs. Aortic
stenosis is left-sided.
Head bopping we
usually see in aortic
regurgitation and
hoarseness doesn't really
apply here. So your
answer will be A. And
here's an explanation
down here as well.
So question two, feel
free to pause and read.
So essentially we want
to figure out what is
the most likely to also
be seen in this patient.
So 40 year old comes
in, weakness, left side,
you start reading
right calf swollen,
long flight, think
DVT immediately.
A lot of the board questions
love DVT presentations
for whatever reason, so
get to be a friend of it.
CT scan shows embolic stroke in
the right middle
cerebral artery.
Typically, if there's
an embolic stroke from a
DVT, there has to be some
form of hole in the heart.
So it's essentially asking
which of the following
is most also likely to
be seen in this patient.
So we need to figure
out A, what could
have caused this kind
of hole to occur?
And it's usually
either a ventricle
septal defect or an
atrial septal defect. More
common atrial because
you could have that shift
back to the right side
pumping into the left.
Doesn't really occur
with ventricular. So A, a
rumbling of mid-diastolic
murmur best heard at
the apex. This is usually
your mitral stenosis.
Continuous machine-like
murmur and bounding peripheral
pulses. Not really. You
hear continuous machine like
think patent ductus arteriosus
low frequency vibratory
ejection systolic murmur
at the left lower sternum
border near the apex is
something actually called a
stills murmur don't worry
about it we didn't review it
here pan systolic
vibratory murmur could be a
regurgitation in the mitral
tricuspid valves or also in the
tricular septal defect and
finally e if you haven't
figured it out wide and fixed
split s2 so again remember
any atrial septal defect
will create a wide and
fixed split s2 heart sound
that's essentially because
there is more preload on the
right side from blood rushing
in from the left atrium
back into the right question
three you can pause and
read it so essentially what
is the underlying mechanism
here so if we read our
prompt. We're going through.
Okay, cool. Dyspnea.
Immigrant from a developing
country moved to the
U.S. 10 years ago.
Typically, board questions
may be referencing
here. They may not have
had access to medications.
They may not have
had all the necessary
vaccines that are
occurring at these states.
Hemodynamic studies show
abnormally elevated pulmonary
capillary wedge pressure
with normal left
ventricular pressure. This is
key because this essentially
tells us the issue is
somewhere in that mitral
valve, because we have
elevated pulmonary capillary
wedge pressure, which also
is a measurement for the
left atrium, but the left
ventricle is normal, so
it has to be a mitral issue.
So which of the following
mechanisms underlies this
patient's most likely
condition? Age-related
valvular calcification, eh,
only 43.
Congenital defect,
maybe, usually you think about
that more with aortic stenosis.
Molecular mimicry,
I like that answer.
Myocardial ischemia,
okay.
I can't rule it
out, but not my best
choice. Papillary
muscle rupture,
somewhat. I don't necessarily
see the regurge
occurring there.
I would expect some
bigger issues with left
ventricular pressure.
Pulmonary arterial thrombi,
that doesn't make
sense because why would
I be having issues
in the left atrium if
I have a thrombus in
the pulmonary artery?
So our answer is going
to be molecular mammary.
And this is again due to
mitral stenosis, most likely
due to rheumatic fever
during childhood. Again, we
have elevated pulmonary
vasculature suggesting issue
on the left side of the
heart. We have an increased
pressure in the left atrium
due to the stenotic valve.
question four feel free
to pause so notice this
is actually the same
question but the prompt is a
little bit different which
of the following best
describes the heart murmur
that this patient most
likely has so we said
it's mitral stenosis so we
can immediately kind of
get rid of a few of these
right?
So mitral stenosis
we would expect to
hear during diastole.
So systolic murmur,
no.
Machine-like murmur,
probably not. Harsh
crescendo decrescendo
ejection murmur,
probably not, right?
Blowing diastolic
murmur best heard at
the left sternal border.
All right, both of
these are pretty
good, but we know
with mitral stenosis
we usually hear
that opening snap.
So our answer is going to D.
So mid-diastolic
rumble with an opening
snap at the apex,
again that's our
mitral stenosis.
The other answers,
systolic murmur at the
right sternal border,
think about aortic
stenosis, right, systole, so
we would throw that out
immediately. Machine
-like, patent ductus
arteriosus, harsh crescendo,
decrescendo, ejection
murmur. That's usually
another kind of term if
you hear ejection murmur
for stenotic or systolic
murmur, my apologies,
so pulmonary valve stenosis.
Blowing diastolic murmur
best heard at the left
sternal border. Think
about pulmonic recurge.
Question five, feel free
to read and then pause.
so big thing here 23 injects
heroin so I'm thinking
IV drug user has a
temperature not great maybe
there's some form of sepsis
going on prominent jugular
vanus pulse and a blowing
systolic heart murmur
loudest at the left lower
sternal border murmur
varies with respiration
becoming louder with inspiration
this is throwing everything
at you guys already
right so most likely
diagnosis. I can eliminate E,
tricuspid regurgitation. So
increases with inspiration
and is a systolic murmur.
Leaves really only
pulmonary valve stenosis
and tricuspid regurgis
options. Patient is an IV
drug user which commonly
causes infective endocarditis
of the tricuspid valve.
Question six.
So I have a 21 year
old female coming to my
office feeling like
she has extra beats
in her chest. No
history of syncope or
presyncope. No risk
factors. No family history.
No signs of symptoms.
Take no medications.
Physical exam. Vital signs
are normal. Lungs are clear.
Three out of six late
systolic murmur is present.
Heard best at the cardiac
apex, so maybe mitral area.
Mid-systolic click is
heard and echocardiogram
confirms the diagnosis of
mitral valve prolapse. Okay,
so which of the following
maneuvers will increase
the intensity of the murmur
and make the click occur
later in systole? So
remember, we spoke about this.
This is essentially going
to be increases or decreases
of preload. We'll change
the timing of the click.
So if you remember,
if I increase the
amount of preload,
it's going to take
longer for that click
volume to occur.
So essentially, if
the click is occurring
later, I need more
preload. So the question
becomes from this fairly
complicated question
to, hey, what maneuver
increases preload?
And if you look at it,
the only one that's really
going to give you a good
answer is D, leg raise.
So mitral valve prolapse
occurs during systole,
and the events that
increase the preload will
decrease the intensity of
the murmur and move the
click of mitral valve
prolapse later in systole.
So that is it. I hope you
all enjoyed my lecture. If
you have any questions,
comments, or concerns, please
feel free to reach out.
Again, I want to thank Dr.
Happel for all of her help
and assistance throughout
this process, and keep
on working. I know second
year is difficult. I know
you all have a lot on your
plates, clubs, volunteering,
lectures. It's a very
difficult semester. Keep
your head up if you ever see
me around campus feel free
to chat about anything.
It wasn't that long ago
I was the second year so
if you ever need anything
please don't hesitate to
reach out. Thank you all
and keep on working hard.